Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Company Offices, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated; 1920-2000; 86 boxes plus oversize containers
  - Office of the President, 1903-2002 and undated; 1950s-1990s
    - Bert Collins, 1943-2002 and undated; 1970s-1994; 23 boxes
      - Other Organizations
        - General Files
          - American Citizens Life Corporation, 1985 Nov. 12, 1988-1990, 1994, 2 folders (Box 56)
          - American Citizens Life Corporation: Board of Directors meeting, annual stockholders meeting announcement, 1991 Apr. (Box 56)
          - American Citizens Life Insurance Corporation: various documents, 1987-1988 (Box 66)
          - American Council of Life Insurance: Life Insurance Company Quality Efforts survey, 1992 (Box 56)
          - American Council of Life Insurance: Proposed regulation, 1990, 7 folders (Box 56)
          - Boys and Girls Club, 1987-1991, 1-2 of 4 folders (Box 56)
          - Boys and Girls Club, 1987-1991, 3-4 of 4 folders (Box 57)
          - Boys and Girls Club: National Council Annual meeting, 1991 (Box 57)
          - Regional meeting, 1994 Apr. 19 (Box 57)
          - CLG, Inc., 1985-1987 (Box 57)
          - Deloitte and Touche, 1984-1990, 2 folders (Box 57)
          - Duke Hypertension Center: Community Advisory Board, 1994 June 25 (Box 57)
          - Duke University Fuqua School of Business, 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 57)
          - Ernst and Young (Ernst and Whinney), 1983-1990, 2 folders (Box 57)
          - External meetings, symposiums, and retreats, 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 57)
          - External memos, reports, and general info, 1989-1990 (Box 57)
          - External memos, reports, and general info, 1990-1994, 10 folders (Box 58)
          - External memos, reports, and general info, 1994, 4 folders (Box 59)
          - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: 1991, 2 folders (Box 59)
          - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: Board of Directors, 1991 (Box 59)
          - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: Finance Committee meeting, 1991 Nov. 7, 2 folders (Box 59)
          - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: Finance Committee minutes, 1991 (Box 59)
          - Guardsmen, 1994 (Box 60)
          - Insurance Achievement - John Allen, 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 60)
            [Five audiocassettes removed to Recordings Series.]
          - J. Brown, Pro Care Insurance Services, Inc., 1994 (Box 60)
          - Leadership Training Institute and Civil Rights Reunion, 1990 Aug. 15-19 (Box 60)
          - Legislative and Salary Study Commission report, 1990 (Box 60)
          - LIC Board Meeting - Chicago, 1994 Sept. 24-25 (Box 60)
          - Major Campaign Review Board, 1991 (Box 60)
          - Mutual Savings and Loan, 1988-1992 and undated (Box 66)
          - NC Business Council, 1991 (Box 60)
          - NC Center for Nonprofits, 1994 (Box 60)
          - North Carolina Airports Association annual meetings, 1991 (Box 60)
          - North Carolina Amateur Sports Board of Directors, 1987-1991 (Box 60)
          - Raison D'Etre Club, 1970-1972 (Box 60)
          - Raleigh Durham Airport, 1990 (Box 60)
          - Richard Genz - Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation, 1992-1993 (Box 60)
          - Total Quality Education, 1994 (Box 60)
          - UDI/CDC Board meeting, 1994 Sept. 28 (Box 60)
          - United Way of Greater Durham Loaned Executive Training, 1992 Aug. 17 (Box 60)
          - Wachovia Board meeting, 1994 Apr. 15 (Box 60)
          - Who's Who in America, 1992-1994 (Box 60)
        - NCM Capital (Box 61)
          - Acquisition, 1991, 5 folders (Box 61)
          - Attorney's fees, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Harper, Wiggins, and Co. Accountants proposal to serve, 1990 (Box 61)
          - Information regarding purchase, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Items due from lease, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Management Group business records and information, 1988-1991, 3 folders (Box 61)
          - By-laws, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Compensation data, 1991 (Box 61)
          - 1991 (Box 61)
          - Corporate meetings, 1990 (Box 61)
          - Information, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 61)
          - Information packets, circa 1988 (Box 62)
          - Executive Committee meeting, 1991 (Box 62)
          - NCM Board resolutions, 1991 (Box 62)
          - Note purchases, 1991 (Box 62)
          - Quarterly report, 1990 (Box 62)
          - Stock and notes, audit info request, 1986-1991 (Box 62)
          - United Asset Management annual report, 1990 (Box 62)
        - North Carolina Central University (Box 63)
          - Academic Affairs annual report, 1990-1991 (Box 63)
          - Board of Trustees, 1988-1994, 7 folders (Box 63)
          - Board of Trustees agendas and meetings, 1990 (Box 63)
          - Board of Trustees info, 1989-1990 (Box 63)
          - Board of Trustees information for Collins, 1990, 2 of 3 folders (Box 63)
          - Board of Trustees information for Collins, 1990, 1 of 3 folders (Box 64)
          - Budget info and case study for the Board of Trustees, 1990 (Box 64)
          - Business Associates Program, 1988-1990 (Box 64)
          - DeJarmon, 1992 Apr. (Box 64)
          - Miscellaneous, 1987-1991, 2 folders (Box 64)
          - NCCU Foundation, 1983, 5 folders (Box 64)
          - NCCU Foundation report, 1991 Apr. 12 (Box 64)
          - Open House, 1992 (Box 64)
          - Records from UNC Board of Governors, 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 65)
          - Records from The University of North Carolina - the 1989 Conference on Trusteeship (Box 65)
          - Printed Material - Feasibility Study, 1984 (Box 65)
          - Printed Material - NCCU Catalog, 1988-1990 (Box 65)
          - School of Law - Board of Visitors, 1975-1990, 2 folders (Box 65)
          - Search Committee, 1991 (Box 65)
          - Trustee Collins, 1991 Apr. (Box 65)
          - UNC Board of Governors, 1993 (Box 65)
          - UNC-CH campus visitation, 1994 Oct. 14 (Box 65)
    - Office of the President Oversize Material
      - Annual statement and clippings, 1965, 1988, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
      - New York Life Insurance Company annual statement, 1959, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
      - Clippings, 1959, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
      - Clippings, 1987-1989, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
      - Clippings, 1994, 2 folders; box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
      - Life/70 Proposal, 1979 Jan. 3, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV2)
      - Retiree information, floor plan markups, 1970, circa 1990, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
      - Fifty leading industrial life companies, 1952, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - Financial statement, casualty statements and reports, 1931, 1961-1965, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - Employer year end reports, 1971-1972, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - Asa T. Spaulding clipping, 1990, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - Floor plans, 1986, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - FAS master schedule, circa 1992, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - The Independent, 1999 Feb. 10-16, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1990-1991, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
      - Carpet layout, 1987, box size: 24x36 inches (Box OV10)
      - Merrick-Moore Scholarship clippings, 1935-1936, box size: 21x25 inches (Box OV38)
      - 1982 net incomes by state and Analysis of operations by lines of business, 1982, box size: 21x25 inches (Box OV38)
      - "Salute to our president / two weeks performance / Washington District," poster board, before 1950?, Measures approximately 19 x 14 7/8 inches. (Oversize-folder 9)
        Hand-lettered sign; board is fragile, handle with care.
        Includes a list of sales figures for top-producing sales agents in the Washington District.
  - Personnel Files, 1950s-1990s
    Files on employees of NC Mutual originally located in the Office of the President Subseries, chiefly created from the 1950s through the 1990s.
    [The Personnel files Subseries is CLOSED to access for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record, or 2074.]
    - Personnel Files (Box 67-68)
  - Public Relations, 1911-2008 and undated; 13 boxes and oversize containers
    Material in files chiefly documents activities such as advertising, publications and printing, and community relations projects undertaken by North Carolina Mutual. The Photographic Material Series also houses an extensive collections of images used by the Public Relations Department in publications such as The Whetstone.
    [Box 70 contains some fragile material that is in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents may need to be photocopied before being handled.]
    - Advertising and Promotions, 1911-1998 and undated
      The bulk of the material dates from the 1980s and consists of bids, invoices, contracts, shipping lists, and correspondence regarding advertising in specific periodicals, radio stations, and television stations. Also included are memos, drafts, sketches, and research regarding advertising strategy, specific advertisements, and promotional events. This subseries also contains clippings, sample ads, and promotional materials, such as calendars and pamphlets, and photographic plates of group shots and advertisements. Other promotional items are housed and described in the Memorabilia and Artifacts Series.
      - Advertising and promotions files, 58 folders (Box 69, 69A, 69B)
    - Community Relations, 1932-2008 and undated
      Documents NCM's various programs and activities related to community outreach through scholarship support, mentoring programs for youth, and community health programs such as anti-smoking campaigns. Materials consist of event programs, pamphlets, clippings, speeches, photographs, certificates, and leaflets. A substantial portion of the materials are related to the Merrick-Moore Scholarship in the 1930s, including lists of colleges and students, bills, receipts, and correspondence from awardees. Also of note are materials related to the Avery Boys' Club, including a binder belonging to W.J. Kennedy, Jr. Other programs and events are related to the United Negro College Fund, NCCU, the Boy Scouts, Greater Durham Arts Fund, a letter from President Reagan, the 1943 launch of the S.S. Merrick, and Founders' Day celebrations.
      - Community Relations files, 53 folders (Box 69B, 70, 70A)
      - Merrick-Moore Memorial Scholarship Fund Ledger, 1935-1942 (Box 187)
        Bound volume of financial transctions
    - Financial Statements, 1966-1968, 1985-1986
      Contains financial reports, annual reports to policyholders, budget statements, advertising expenditures, and periodicals.
      - Financial statements files, 13 folders (Box 70A, 70B)
    - Heritage Room, 1975-1983 and undated
      Contains correspondence, clippings, layout plans, and photographs related to the creation of NCM's Heritage Room, a large exhibit on company history.
      - Heritage Room files, 3 folders (Box 70B)
    - Historical Files, 1927-2008
      The bulk of the material is related to specific events, such as annual meetings, the ground-breaking ceremony in 1963, and the celebration of NCM's 85th anniversary, centennial, material for tribute honoring Dr. William and Stella Cleland, script material for television episode regarding N.C. Mutual and John Merrick, and various Founders' Days. Materials consist of slides, photographs, clippings, correspondence, programs, print materials, memos, and other planning documents. Also included are historic NCM policies and certificates.
      - Historical files, 20 folders (Box 70B, 71)
    - Other Correspondence, 1973-1996
      Files of mixed correspondence concerning the Public Relations Department. The bulk of the files date from 1984-1986. Materials also include solicitations, brochures, and subscription forms. Topics include radio and television stations, interview requests, A.T. Spaulding, Ben Ruffin, and W.J. Kennedy, Jr.
      - Correspondence files, 35 folders (Box 72, 73)
    - Other Files, 1984-1986 and undated
      Additional materials created by the Public Relations Department that do not fit in above categories. Topics include office contests, employee benefits, taxation, the donations committee, smoking cessation program files, the new products committee, the lyrics to the company song, and the history of African Methodism. Materials include phone messages, personnel forms, notes, agenda, minutes, memoranda, brochures, correspondence, an architecture showcase book, a drawing of a house, information collected regarding Hispanics, and a memoir about life insurance.
      - Other Public Relations files, 38 folders (Box 73, 74, 75)
    - Personnel, 1933-2004
      Files open to research access contain company publicity regarding personnel, including, but not limited to, obituaries, biographies, a list of employee birthdays, and other announcements. Among those profiled are Asa T. Spaulding, C.C. Spaulding, Jr., William Henry Harvey, W.E. Williams, W.E. Coleman, W.D. Hill, J.L. Wheeler, W. Lionel Cook, and Fred R. Moore. Several folders related to the retirement and death of William Kennedy, Jr. contain extensive photographs alongside paper materials. Folders profiling women associated with NCM contain copies of The Whetstone and photographs from the 2000s.
      - Personnel files, 18 folders (Box 75)
    - Press Coverage and Press Releases, 1938-2004
      Contains press releases put out by the Public Relations Department and clippings, photocopies, and reprints of articles about NCM and its staff, including entire issues of several mass market magazines.
      - Press coverage and press releases files, 24 folders (Box 75, 76)
    - Production and Publications, 1931-1986
      Contains copies of The Review, pages from The Whetstone, ad layouts, proofs, photos, correspondence, notes, memos, and other files relating to Public Relations publishing and printing workflows.
      - Production and publications files, 15 folders (Box 76)
    - Speeches, 1953-1973
      Contains copies of speeches, press releases, and interviews with Presidents William J. Kennedy, Jr., J.L. Goodloe, and Asa T. Spaulding. Also includes speeches by various public figures at the home office dedication in 1966.
      - Speeches files, 10 folders (Box 76, 77)
    - Public Relations Oversize Material
      - Calendar, circa 1940, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
      - Calendar art, A Penny Short, NC Mutual presidents, painting of building, undated, box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
      - Sell-E-Bration poster, 1962 July-Aug., box size: 22x30 inches (Box OV1)
      - Advertisements, mounted on foamcore, after 1990, box size: 24x30 inches; 2 items (Box OV52)
        Two large panels mounted on foamcore: "Building your family's future" (color image of African American family of four), and "Employee benefits provider," benefits lists in large black-and-white text.
      - NC Mutual advertisement panel, after 1990, box size: 24x30 inches (Box OV52)
        Large panel mounted on foamcore board with prop on back: "Building your family's future" (color image of African American man with child riding on shoulders), copy 1
      - NC Mutual advertisement panel, after 1990, box size: 24x30 inches (Box OV52)
        Large panel mounted on foamcore board with prop on back: "Building your family's future" (color image of African American man with child riding on shoulders), copy 2
      - Advertisements, undated, box size: 16x20 inches (Box OV4)
      - Advertising sketch by Nash, undated, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV9)
      - Calendars, 1968-2008, box size: 24x36 inches; 2 folders (Box OV10)
      - Calendars, 1930-1939, 1968-1976, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV11)
      - Calendars, 1977-1984, 1990, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV11)
      - Posters, calendars, art, 1946-1999, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV11)
      - Advertisements in newspapers and ads for agents, 1962-1977, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV12)
      - Asa T. Spaulding clippings, 1956-1972, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV12)
      - Budgets, 1984-1986, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV12)
      - Clippings, 1950-1991, 3 folders; box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV12)
      - Programs, advertisements, clippings, 1927-1982, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV12)
      - Ad ideas and planning, 1972-1982 and undated, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV12)
      - Advertisements and proofs, 1962-1968, box size: 14x18 inches; 2 folders (Box OV13)
      - Durham Arts Council classes, 1986, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV13)
      - NCCU presidential inauguration, 1968, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV13)
      - Brown and Bigelow calendar enclosure, 1960, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV13)
      - NIA 50th anniversary, 1970, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV13)
      - Newspapers and clippings, 1983-1986, box size: 14x18 inches; 4 folders (Box OV13)
      - The Whetstone layout, 1993, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV13)
      - NCM wall calendars, 1989, 1992, 1999-2006, box size: 21x25 inches (Box OV38)
      - Board of Directors, Past and Present, 1946, box size: 23x31 inches (Box OV45)
      - Calendar art, A Penny Short painting reproduction, copyright 1936, box size: 23x31 inches (Box OV45)
      - Calendars, 1927-1928, 1936-1938, box size: 23x31 inches (Box OV45)
      - Magazine advertisements (bound), 1975-1978, box size: 14x20 inches (Box OV49)
      - Charlotte, NC branch advertisement, ca. 1911, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV13)
      - Very large posters and advertisements, 1968-2006, 14 items (Oversize-folder 1-3)
- Corporate History Files, 1900-2005; 2 boxes
  Assembled by staff of NC Mutual and a former company archivist, these files contain a sampling of the most significant historical documents illustrating the formation of the company, its founders, and its first decade of existence. Materials are varied and include charters and by-laws; early policies, publications and advertisements; significant correspondence; programs, annual statements, and Christmas greetings; items marking milestones in company history; and other unique items. There is also a folder with two charts for 1933 and 1941 ranking the current African American owned life insurance companies, including NCM. Other historical and early items can also be found throughout the collection, especially in the Agency, Memorabilia, Photographic Material, and Print Material Series, and the Office of the President Subseries; early examples of policies from 1902 into the 1930s are found in the Agency Series. Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Bylaws and amendments, 1900-1946 (Box 78)
  - Annual statement, 1908 (Box 78)
  - The Mutual Album, 1910 (Box 78)
  - Home office postcard, circa 1910 (Box 78)
  - Amendment of Charter documents, 1912-1914, 4 folders (Box 78)
  - Agents' conference, 1920 June (Box 78)
  - Publications and pamphlets, 1920-1923 (Box 78)
  - Female employees, 1923-1995 (Box 78)
  - Greetings, statements, and advertisements, 1924-1927 (Box 78)
  - "Meet the Who's Who of the Company's Officials," after 1926, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
    Portraits of 10 NCM leaders. Photocopy.
  - C.C. Spaulding speeches and other materials, 1926-1935 (Box 78)
  - Clippings from newspapers regarding NCM, after 1926-1946, 4 folders (Box 78)
  - Publications, pamphlets, and advertisements, 1927-1929 (Box 78)
  - Biographical sketches of officers and directors, 1927-1969 (Box 78)
  - Annual statement, 1928 (Box 78)
  - Manuscript and quotations, 1928 and undated (Box 78)
  - Liberia banknote, 1929 Jan. 31 (Box 78)
  - Publications, correspondence, advertisements, and statements, 1930-1938 (Box 78)
  - Records of life insurance enterprises operated by Negroes, 1933, 1941 (2 charts with data such as assets, founding date) (Box 78)
  - The Negro's Adventure in the Field of Life Insurance, by W.J. Kennedy, Jr., 1934 (Box 78)
  - Historical Sketch, by W.J. Kennedy Jr., 1934 (Box 78)
  - Thrift Club manual, 1938 (Box 78)
  - Charter and amendments, 1938-1946, 4 folders (Box 79)
  - Chronology, 1938 (Box 79)
  - The President's Book, 1939 (Box 79)
  - Correspondence, statements, and programs, 1940-1949 (Box 79)
  - A Tour of the Home Office, 1945-1955 (Box 79)
  - Whaley's Pharmacy grand opening, 1951 Oct. 11 (Box 79)
  - Historical summary of provisions governing payment analysis, 1952 (Box 79)
  - Publications and memos on NCM history, 1952-2005 (Box 79)
  - Proofs from publication on NCM history, undated (Box 79)
  - Speeches, publications, and programs, 1953-1966 (Box 79)
  - Bylaws of NCM and other companies, 1957 (Box 79)
  - Draft of NCM bylaws, 1958 and undated (Box 79)
  - Bylaws and charter committee, 1963-1971 (Box 79)
  - Organizational Survey of the Home Office, 1963 Aug. (Box 79)
  - Presidents' biographical sketches, circa 1990 (Box 79)
  - 1909 annual statement, photocopied in 1964 with note from 1983, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV8)
  - Holding Companies Paperwork, 1983-2000; 2 folders (Box 187)
    Includes official correspondence between NCM and various companies and government agencies
  - Bylaws of NCM, 1984 (Box 187)
- Digital Media, 2000s; 3 boxes
  Contains diskettes of files and DVDs with photographic images and duplicated historical films, chiefly regarding NC Mutual's history. Titles taken from original media carriers.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original media are closed to use. Access to electronic files may be requested in advance and may be viewed only in the Rubenstein reading room.
  Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
  - Diskettes, 30 items Number of items is approximate
    - Electronic files from NCM offices (Box DIG 1)
  - DVDs
    - 10 DVDs with files of images and documents, and a documentary about "Black Wall Street" in Durham NC (Box DIG 2)
  - 6 DVD carriers containing copies of films
    - Dedication, 1966 (Box DIG 3)
    - Three color shorts, 1966 (Box DIG 3)
    - Dedication, TV, 1966 (Box DIG 3)
    - Groundbreaking, circa 1963 (Box DIG 3)
    - 75th Anniversary, 1975 (Box DIG 3)
    - DC footage, about 1970 (Box DIG 3)
- Exhibit Materials, 1940s, 1960s-2000s, and undated; 1970s-2000s; 25 boxes
  Houses the components of the many exhibits assembled and curated by North Carolina Mutual staff, most of which were part of a large exhibit on NCM history in the company's Heritage Gallery in the Mutual Building on Chapel Hill Street in Durham. Other exhibits were created for specific events such as conventions.
  Mostly consists of black and white or sepia images and captions reproduced from original photographs and mounted on thin board, often with velcro backing. A good selection are from vintage photographs from the early years of the company. Later images, some in color, show officers and employees in meetings, conferring, or posing for portraits. Finally, some exhibit panels are reproductions of advertisements and other broadsides. The exhibit boxes also house large groups of caption cards, labels, and informational panels.
  This group also includes two framed letters of interest: one from Eleanor Roosevelt's secretary, writing in July 1934 subsequent to a visit to NCM by Roosevelt in June of that year, and the other a strongly worded letter written by President Spaulding on improving the company's performance, entitled "Open Letter to Managers," from Berlin, Germany, 1931.
  Thousands of additional images illustrating the company's history are housed in the Photographic Materials Series, including original photographs from which the exhibit images were reproduced. Some additional exhibit materials may be found in this series.
  - Exhibit materials: panels, images, and captions (in original order as received), 1980s? (Box 80-89)